我们讨论了如何线性插值位置。
We talked about how we can linearly interpolate position.
我们如何处理轮换？
What do we do for the case of rotations?
我们可以天真地重写我们的表达式，我们有初始旋转，即
We could naively rewrite our expression like this where we have the initial rotation, the
最终旋转和中间旋转。
final rotation and the intermediate rotation.
但是，这个方案存在问题。
But, there’s a problem with this scheme.
旋转矩阵不仅仅是任何旧的3x3矩阵。
A rotation matrix is not just any old 3 x 3 matrix.
这是一个特殊的矩阵。
It’s a special matrix.
它是一个正交矩阵，这意味着矩阵中的每一列都是一个单位向量。
It’s an orthogonal matrix and that means that each column in the matrix is a unit vector.
因此，如果我添加两个正交矩阵，结果永远不会是正交矩阵，因为
So if I add two orthogonal matrices, the result will never be an orthogonal matrix because
如果我能看到每一列，两个单位向量的总和，永远不会是一个单位
if I can see that each column, the sum of two unit vectors, can never ever be a unit
向量。
vector.
所以这不是我们可以用来插值旋转的策略。
So this is not a strategy we can use to interpolate rotations.
我们需要考虑其他表示我们可以插值的旋转的方法。
We need to consider other ways of representing rotation that we can interpolate.
因此，实现此目的的一种方法是回想一下这个插值公式适用于向量
So, one way to achieve this is to recall that this interpolation formula works for vectors
我们可以用角度矢量表示旋转。
and we can represent a rotation in terms of a vector of angles.
它可以是三个欧拉角或者它可以是三个滚动，俯仰，偏转角。
It can be three Euler angles or it could be three roll, pitch, yaw angles.
因此，如果我们将这个角度向量视为符号Gamma，那么我们可以引入
So if we consider this vector of angles as the symbol Gamma, then we can introduce the
初始角度，最终角度，然后我们可以插入中间角度。
initial angles, the final angles, and then we can interpolate the intermediate angles.
如果我们的初始和最终方向是根据旋转矩阵给出的话
If our initial and final orientations are given in terms of rotation matrices, then
我们将这两者转换为初始角度集和最终角度集。
we convert those two into initial set of angles and a final set of angles.
我们插入中间角度，然后我们可以将它们转换回旋转矩阵
We interpolate the intermediate angles and we can convert those back to a rotation matrix
如果我们这么渴望。
if we so desire.
我们将使用我们刚才看到的函数jtraj来插入roll，
We’re going to use the function jtraj that we looked at a moment ago to interpolate roll,
俯仰，偏航角度。
pitch, yaw angles.
我将把结果放入工作空间变量X.调用jtraj函数。
I’m going to put the result into the workspace variable X. Invoke the jtraj function.
我将在一组滚动，俯仰，偏航角度和滚动等于之间进行插值
I’m going to interpolate between a set of roll, pitch, yaw angles and roll equal to
0和最后一组滚动，俯仰，偏航角等于2的负pi，再加上pi
0 and the final set of roll, pitch, yaw angles which are equal to minus pi on 2, plus pi
在2和pi在4。
on 2 and pi on 4.
而且，我将在一百多个步骤中进行插值。
And, I’m going to do this interpolation over a hundred time steps.
结果是我们工作区中的一个新变量有100行，每行对应
The result is a new variable in our workspace that’s got 100 rows, each row corresponds
到了一个时间步。
to a time step.
并且，它有三列，列对应于滚动，俯仰和偏航角度。
And, it has got three columns and the columns correspond to the roll, pitch and yaw angles.
我可以绘制这个滚动，俯仰，偏航角度与时间的关系。
I can plot this roll, pitch, yaw angles versus time.
在这里，我们可以看到它们的样子，从初始值顺利移动到最终值
Here we can see what they look like, moving smoothly from the initial value to the final
值。
value.
现在，我们想要将矩阵X的每一行中的滚动，俯仰，偏航角度转换为a
Now, we want to convert the roll, pitch, yaw angle in each row of the matrix X in to a
旋转矩阵。
rotation matrix.
为此，我将使用我们之前查看过的rpy2r函数
And to do that, I’m going to use the rpy2r function that we looked at previously and
我打算通过X.
I’m going to pass in X.
在这种情况下，函数将执行的是它将转换此矩阵的每一行
And what the function will do in this case is it will convert every row of this matrix
进入旋转矩阵。
into a rotation matrix.
结果是旋转矩阵，但矩阵的尺寸为3x3x100。
The result is a rotation matrix, but the matrix has got dimensions of 3 x 3 x 100.
所以我们可以把它想象成一堆旋转矩阵。
So we can think of it as a stack of rotation matrices.
所以我们可以查看该堆栈中的第一个，它是一个旋转矩阵。
So we could look at the first one in that stack and it’s a rotation matrix.
看起来像这样。
It looks like this.
它是空转。
It’s null rotation.
这是一个单位矩阵。
It’s a unit matrix.
我可以看看堆栈中的第10个，它看起来像这样。
I could look at the 10th one in the stack and it looks something like this.
所以R是一系列旋转矩阵。
So R is a sequence of rotation matrices.
现在我可以将一系列旋转矩阵传递给函数tranimate。
Now I can pass a sequence of rotation matrices like that to the function tranimate.
我们将看到的是一个动画，显示坐标系的方向发生变化
What we will see is an animation showing the orientation of the coordinate frame changing
从滚动，俯仰，偏航角度指定的最初方向平滑到最终
smoothly from the initial orientation specified in terms of roll, pitch, yaw angles to a final
方向也在滚动，俯仰，偏航角度方面指定。
orientation also specified in terms of roll, pitch, yaw angles.
欧拉角和滚动，俯仰，偏航角表示为三个角度的矢量。
Euler angles and roll, pitch, yaw angles are represented as a vector of three angles.
我们可以将这些向量的每个元素视为一个圆上的点和来自的路径
Each element of these vectors we can consider as a point on a circle and the path from the
最终角度的初始角度是单位圆上的弧。
initial angle to the final angle is an arc on the unit circle.
现在考虑我们有这个初始角度和最终角度的情况。
Consider now the case where we have this initial angle and this final angle.
而天真的插值会将我们从初始角度移动到最终角度
And a naive interpolation would move us from the initial angle to the final angle the long
围绕圈子的方式。
way around the circle.
我们需要记住的角度是，总有两种方法可以从A到达
What we need to remember with angles is that there are always two ways to get from A to
B.
可能还有很长的路要走，可能还有很短的路要走。
There is potentially the long way and there is potentially the short way.
因此，当我们在角度序列向量中插入每个元素时，这很重要
So when we are interpolating each element in our angle sequence vector, it’s important
我们选择最短的路径。
that we choose the shortest path.
如果我们将角度视为时间的函数，则长路径在此处以蓝色显示。
If we look at the angle as a function of time, the long path is given here in blue.
我们看到我们正在从2弧度移动到-2弧度。
We see we’re moving from 2 radians to -2 radians.
而以红色显示的短路径移动通过pi弧度，pop的角度
Whereas the short path which is shown in red moves through an angle of pi radians, pops
返回负π弧度，然后快速移动到值为-2的目标点B.
back at minus pi radians and then moves quickly to the destination point B of a value of -2
弧度。
radians.
早些时候，我们引入四元数，这是我们用来插值的方程式
Earlier, we introduce quaternions and this is the equation we used to interpolate between
两个四元数。
two quaternions.
再一次，它是S和S的函数，从0到1不等。
Once again, it’s a function of S and S varies from 0 to 1.
而这个等式中的重要元素是Theta和Theta来自元素
And the important element in this equation is Theta and Theta is derived from the elements
初始和最终四元数。
of the initial and final quaternion.
这被称为球面线性插值，它是最短且最直接的路径
This is referred to as spherical linear interpolation and it is the shortest and most direct path
在任何两个方向之间。
between any two orientations.
并且它对应于围绕空间中的固定轴的恒定角速度。
And it corresponds to a constant angular velocity about a fixed axis in space.
让我们创建一对四元数，我们将在它们之间进行插值。
Let’s create a pair of quaternions that we will interpolate between.
第一个对应于空旋转。
The first one corresponds to a null rotation.
我们看到它的矢量分量为0。
We see that it’s got a vector component of 0.
第二个四元数表示通过pi在2上围绕x轴的旋转。
The second quaternion is a representation of a rotation about the x-axis by pi on 2.
所以，我们将传递一个旋转矩阵。
So, we’re going to pass in a rotation matrix.
四元数类将把它变成四元数。
The quaternion class is going to turn that into a quaternion.
现在，我们的工作区中有两个四元数，一个对应于无旋转，一个对应
Now, there are two quaternions in our workspace, one corresponding to no rotation, one corresponding
围绕x轴旋转90度。
to rotation of 90 degrees about the x-axis.
要插入四元数，我们使用interp方法。
To interpolate quaternions, we use the interp method.
我们将其应用于初始四元数。
We apply that to the initial quaternion.
并且，第一个参数是最终的四元数，第二个参数是位置
And, the first argument is the final quaternion and the second argument is the position along
一条轨迹。
a trajectory.
所以0是轨迹上的第一个点。
So 0 is the first point on the trajectory.
这是初始条件，初始四元数是空转。
That’s the initial condition, the initial quaternion which is the null rotation.
我可以重复一遍，并要求插值中的最后一点，这等于
I can repeat that and ask for the final point in the interpolation and that is equal to
第二个四元数。
the second quaternion.
我现在可以问一个点在0.5之间的中间点，这就是插值的四元数。
I can ask now for a point that’s midway between 0.5 and this is the interpolated quaternion.
当然，我可以使用R方法将其转回旋转矩阵。
And of course, I can turn that back in to a rotation matrix using the R method.
现在，我们可能想比较不同类型的旋转插值的效果
Now, we might like to compare the effect of the different types of rotational interpolation
这有点困难。
and that’s a little bit difficult.
很难想象出特定的旋转。
It’s hard to visualize a particular rotation.
但是，我们能够做到的一种方法是考虑旋转对特定向量的影响。
But, one way we can do it is to consider the effect of a rotation on a particular vector.
所以在这里，我选择了x轴，我可以用向量1,0,0来表示。
So here, I have chosen the x-axis which I can represent by a vector 1, 0, 0.
我可以将这三种不同的旋转序列应用于该向量。
And I can apply these three different rotation sequences to that vector.
我可以插入初始和最终的欧拉角度，初始和最终的滚动，俯仰，
I can interpolate the initial and final Euler angles, the initial and final roll, pitch,
偏航角或初始和最终四元数，它们由不同颜色显示
yaw angles or the initial and final quaternions and they are shown by the different colored
这里绘制的零件在球体上。
parts plotted here on the sphere.
以白色显示的四元数路径是最短且最直接的路径。
The quaternion path shown in white is the shortest and most direct path.
我们可以看到滚动，俯仰，偏航插补路径已经明显偏离它。
We can see that the roll, pitch, yaw interpolation path has deviated significantly from it.
它从一开始就采取了更为间接和更长的路径
It has taken a more indirect and longer path to get from the initial orientation to the
最终定位。
final orientation.
四元数插值是黄金标准。
Quaternion interpolation is the gold standard.